They could be the hottest accessory of an even hotter summer.
As temperature records were smashed across Europe and other parts of the world, portable electric fans could be seen in the hands of millions of people.
Estimates claim that up to 8 million of these devices were sold in the UK alone.
The breeze that they provide will have been welcome to many, but could there be a downside to this popular product?
Concerns have been raised that these fans are just another example of fast technology.
That is products that are sold cheaply and are likely to be disposed of quickly.
Research from Material Focus, a British pro-recycling organisation, suggests that half of all the mini fans bought will end up unused or thrown away.
This is unsurprising as they can be cheap to buy and almost impossible to repair.
Fans contain a mix of different materials – plastic casing, copper wiring and a lithium-ion battery among other components.
This means that a considerable amount of natural resource is used in their production, and that they can be complex to recycle and dispose of sustainably.
There are more immediate safety risks from portable fans.
The London Fire Brigade has reported cases of cheaply-made portable fan batteries catching fire or exploding while being charged.
Waste disposal companies in the UK have warned that the lithium-ion batteries used by these devices are often thrown away together with household waste, and that this can lead to fires which put staff and installations at risk.
It's not just fire either.
The Japanese Consumer Affairs Agency reports a train passenger's hair being sucked into someone else's fan on a train.
In addition, once the air around you gets hot enough, fans can even make you warmer rather than colder.
As the world's climate continues to heat up, more and more of us may be tempted to reach for portable fans.
But maybe we should take some time to reflect on the effect this might be having on our environment and climate.